BGFX Effects for (nearly) Everyone

Introduction

By default, MAME outputs an idealized version of the video as it would be on the way to the arcade cabinet’s monitor, with minimal modification of the output (primarily to stretch the game image back to the aspect ratio the monitor would traditionally have, usually 4:3). This works well, but misses some of the nostalgia factor. Arcade monitors were never ideal, even in perfect condition, and the nature of a CRT display distorts that image in ways that change the appearance significantly.

Modern LCD monitors simply do not look the same, and even computer CRT monitors cannot match the look of an arcade monitor without help.

That’s where the new BGFX renderer with HLSL comes into the picture.

HLSL simulates most of the effects that a CRT arcade monitor has on the video, making the result look a lot more authentic. However, HLSL requires some effort on the user’s part: the settings you use are going to be tailored to your PC’s system specs, and especially the monitor you’re using. Additionally, there were hundreds of thousands of monitors out there in arcades. Each was tuned and maintained differently, meaning there is no one correct appearance to judge by either. Basic guidelines will be provided here to help you, but you may also wish to ask for opinions on popular MAME-centric forums.

Resolution and Aspect Ratio

Resolution is a very important subject for HLSL settings. You will want MAME to be using the native resolution of your monitor to avoid additional distortion and lag caused by your monitor upscaling the display image.

While most arcade machines used a 4:3 ratio display (or 3:4 for vertically oriented monitors like Pac-Man), it’s difficult to find a consumer display that is 4:3 at this point. The good news is that that extra space on the sides isn’t wasted. Many arcade cabinets used bezel artwork around the main display, and should you have the necessary artwork files, MAME will display that artwork. Turn the Zoom to Screen Area setting in the video options menu to scale and crop the artwork so the emulated screen fills your display in one direction.

Some older LCD displays used a native resolution of 1280×1024 and were a 5:4 aspect ratio. There’s not enough extra space to display artwork, and you’ll end up with some very slight pillarboxing, but the results will be still be good and on-par with a 4:3 monitor.

Getting Started with BGFX

You will need to have followed the initial MAME setup instructions elsewhere in this manual before beginning. Official MAME distributions include BGFX as of MAME 0.172, so you don’t need to download any additional files.

Open your mame.ini file in your text editor of choice (e.g. Notepad), and make sure the following options are set correctly:

video bgfx

Now, you may want to take a moment to look below at the Configuration Settings section to see how to set up these next options.

As explained in Order of Config Loading, MAME has a order in which it processes INI files. The BGFX settings can be edited in mame.ini, but to take full advantage of the power of MAME’s configuration files, you’ll want to copy the BGFX settings from mame.ini to one of the other configuration files and make changes there.

In particular, you will want the bgfx_screen_chains to be specific to each game.

Save your INI file(s) and you’re ready to begin.

Configuration Settings

bgfx_path

This is where your BGFX shader files are stored. By default, this will be the bgfx folder in your MAME installation folder.

bgfx_backend

Selects a rendering backend for BGFX to use. Possible choices include auto, d3d9, d3d11, d3d12, opengl, gles, metal, and vulkan. The default is auto, which will let MAME choose the best selection for you.

d3d9 -- Direct3D 9.0 Renderer (Requires Windows XP or higher)

d3d11 -- Direct3D 11.0 Renderer (Requires Windows Vista with Direct3D 11 update, or Windows 7 or higher)

d3d12 -- Direct3D 12.0 Renderer (Requires Windows 10 or higher)

opengl -- OpenGL Renderer (Requires OpenGL drivers, may work better on some video cards, supported on Linux and macOS)

gles -- OpenGL ES Renderer (Supported with some low-power GPUs)

metal -- Apple Metal Graphics API (Requires macOS 10.11 El Capitan or newer)

vulkan -- Vulkan Renderer (Requires Windows or Linux with compatible GPU drivers.

auto -- MAME will automatically choose the best selection for you.

bgfx_debug

Enables BGFX debugging features. Most users will not need to use this.

bgfx_screen_chains

This dictates how to handle BGFX rendering on a per-display basis. Possible choices include hlsl, unfiltered, and default.

default -- default bilinear filtered output

unfiltered -- nearest neighbor sampled output

hlsl -- display simulation through shaders

crt-geom -- lightweight CRT simulation

crt-geom-deluxe -- more detailed CRT simulation

lcd-grid -- LCD matrix simulation

We make a distinction between emulated screens (which we’ll call a screen) and output windows or monitors (which we’ll call a window, set by the -numscreens option) here. Use colons (:) to separate windows, and commas (,) to separate screens in the -bgfx_screen_chains setting value.

For the simple single window, single screen case, such as Pac-Man on one physical PC monitor, you can specify one entry like:

bgfx_screen_chains hlsl

Things get only slightly more complicated when we get to multiple windows and multiple screens.

On a single window, multiple screen game, such as Darius on one physical PC monitor, specify screen chains (one per window) like:

bgfx_screen_chains hlsl,hlsl,hlsl

This also works with single screen games where you are mirroring the output to more than one physical display. For instance, you could set up Pac-Man to have one unfiltered output for use with video broadcasting while a second display is set up HLSL for playing on.

On a multiple window, multiple screen game, such as Darius on three physical PC monitors, specify multiple entries (one per window) like:

bgfx_screen_chains hlsl:hlsl:hlsl

Another example game would be Taisen Hot Gimmick, which used two CRTs to show individual player hands to just that player. If using two windows (two physical displays):

bgfx_screen_chains hlsl:hlsl

One more special case is that Nichibutsu had a special cocktail mahjong cabinet that used a CRT in the middle along with two LCD displays to show each player their hand. We would want the LCDs to be unfiltered and untouched as they were, while the CRT would be improved through HLSL. Since we want to give each player their own full screen display (two physical monitors) along with the LCD, we’ll go with:

-numscreens 2 -view0 "Player 1" -view1 "Player 2" -video bgfx -bgfx_screen_chains hlsl,unfiltered:hlsl,unfiltered

This sets up the view for each display respectively, keeping HLSL effect on the CRT for each window (physical display) while going unfiltered for the LCD screens.

If using only one window (one display), keep in mind the game still has three screens, so we would use:

bgfx_screen_chains hlsl,unfiltered,unfiltered

Note that the commas are on the outside edges, and any colons are in the middle.

bgfx_shadow_mask

This specifies the shadow mask effect PNG file. By default this is slot-mask.png.

Tweaking BGFX HLSL Settings inside MAME

Start by loading MAME with the game of your choice (e.g. mame pacman).

The tilde key (~) brings up the on-screen display options. Use up and down to go through the various settings, while left and right will allow you to change that setting. Results will be shown in real time as you’re changing these settings.

Note that settings are individually changeable on a per-screen basis.

BGFX slider settings are saved per-system in CFG files. If the bgfx_screen_chains setting has been set (either in an INI file or on the command line), it will set the initial effects. If the bgfx_screen_chains setting has not been set, MAME will use the effects you chose the last time you ran the system.

Using the included pillarbox filters

MAME includes example BGFX shaders and layouts for filling unused space on a 16:9 widescreen display with a blurred version of the emulated video. The all the necessary files are included, and just need to be enabled.

For systems using 4:3 horizontal monitors, use these options:

-override_artwork bgfx/border_blur -view Horizontal -bgfx_screen_chains crt-geom,pillarbox_left_horizontal,pillarbox_right_horizontal

For systems using 3:4 vertical monitors, use these options:

-override_artwork bgfx/border_blur -view Vertical -bgfx_screen_chains crt-geom,pillarbox_left_vertical,pillarbox_right_vertical

You can use a different setting in place of crt-geom for the effect to apply to the primary screen image in the centre (e.g. default, hlsl or lcd-grid).

If you’ve previously changed the view for the system in MAME, the correct pillarboxed view will not be selected by default. Use the video options menu to select the correct view.

You can add these settings to an INI file to have them apply to certain systems automatically (e.g. horizont.ini or vertical.ini, or the INI file for a specific system).

GLSL Effects for *nix, OS X, and Windows

By default, MAME outputs an idealized version of the video as it would be on the way to the arcade cabinet's monitor, with minimal modification of the output (primarily to stretch the game image back to the aspect ratio the monitor would traditionally have, usually 4:3) -- this works well, but misses some of the nostalgia factor. Arcade monitors were never ideal, even in perfect condition, and the nature of a CRT display distorts that image in ways that change the appearance significantly.

Modern LCD monitors simply do not look the same, and even computer CRT monitors cannot match the look of an arcade monitor without help.

That's where GLSL comes into the picture.

GLSL simulates most of the effects that a CRT arcade monitor has on the video, making the result look a lot more authentic. However, GLSL requires some effort on the user's part: the settings you use are going to be tailored to your PC's system specs, and especially the monitor you're using. Additionally, there were hundreds of thousands of monitors out there in arcades. Each was tuned and maintained differently, meaning there is no one correct appearance to judge by either. Basic guidelines will be provided here to help you, but you may also wish to ask for opinions on popular MAME-centric forums.

Resolution and Aspect Ratio

Resolution is a very important subject for GLSL settings. You will want MAME to be using the native resolution of your monitor to avoid additional distortion and lag created by your monitor upscaling the display image.

While most arcade machines used a 4:3 ratio display (or 3:4 for vertically oriented monitors like Pac-Man), it's difficult to find a consumer display that is 4:3 at this point. The good news is that that extra space on the sides isn't wasted. Many arcade cabinets used bezel artwork around the main display, and should you have the necessary artwork files, MAME will display that artwork. Turn the artwork view to Cropped for best results.

Some older LCD displays used a native resolution of 1280x1024, which is a 5:4 aspect ratio. There's not enough extra space to display artwork, and you'll end up with some very slight pillarboxing, but the results will be on-par with a 4:3 monitor.

Getting Started with GLSL

You will need to have followed the initial MAME setup instructions elsewhere in this manual before beginning. Official MAME distributions include GLSL support by default, but do NOT include the GLSL shader files. You will need to obtain the shader files from third party online sources.

Open your mame.ini in your text editor of choice (e.g. Notepad), and make sure the following options are set correctly:

video opengl

filter 0

The former is required because GLSL requires OpenGL support. The latter turns off extra filtering that interferes with GLSL output.

Lastly, one more edit will turn GLSL on:

gl_glsl 1

Save the .INI file and you're ready to begin.

Tweaking GLSL Settings inside MAME

For multiple, complicated to explain reasons, GLSL settings are no longer saved when you exit MAME. This means that while tweaking settings is a little more work on your part, the results will always come out as expected.

Start by loading MAME with the game of your choice (e.g. mame pacman)

The tilde key (~) brings up the on-screen display options. Use up and down to go through the various settings, while left and right will allow you to change that setting. Results will be shown in real time as you're changing these settings.

Once you've found settings you like, write the numbers down on a notepad and exit MAME.

Configuration Editing

As referenced in Order of Config Loading, MAME has a order in which it processes INI files. The GLSL settings can be edited in mame.ini, but to take full advantage of the power of MAME's config files, you'll want to copy the GLSL settings from mame.ini to one of the other config files and make changes there.

For instance, once you've found GLSL settings you think are appropriate for Neo Geo games, you can put those settings into neogeo.ini so that all Neo-Geo games will be able to take advantage of those settings without needing to add it to every game INI manually.

Configuration Settings

gl_glsl

Enables GLSL when set to 1, disabled if set to 0. Defaults to 0.

gl_glsl_filter

Enables filtering to GLSL output. Reduces jagginess at the cost of blurriness.

glsl_shader_mame0

...

glsl_shader_mame9

Specifies the shaders to run, in the order from 0 to 9. See your shader pack author for details on which to run in which order for best effect.

glsl_shader_screen0

...

glsl_shader_screen9

Specifies screen to apply the shaders on.

HLSL Effects for Windows

By default, MAME outputs an idealized version of the video as it would be on the way to the arcade cabinet's monitor, with minimal modification of the output (primarily to stretch the game image back to the aspect ratio the monitor would traditionally have, usually 4:3) -- this works well, but misses some of the nostalgia factor. Arcade monitors were never ideal, even in perfect condition, and the nature of a CRT display distorts that image in ways that change the appearance significantly.

Modern LCD monitors simply do not look the same, and even computer CRT monitors cannot match the look of an arcade monitor without help.

That's where HLSL comes into the picture.

HLSL simulates most of the effects that a CRT arcade monitor has on the video, making the result look a lot more authentic. However, HLSL requires some effort on the user's part: the settings you use are going to be tailored to your PC's system specs, and especially the monitor you're using. Additionally, there were hundreds of thousands of monitors out there in arcades. Each was tuned and maintained differently, meaning there is no one correct appearance to judge by either. Basic guidelines will be provided here to help you, but you may also wish to ask for opinions on popular MAME-centric forums.

Resolution and Aspect Ratio

Resolution is a very important subject for HLSL settings. You will want MAME to be using the native resolution of your monitor to avoid additional distortion and lag created by your monitor upscaling the display image.

While most arcade machines used a 4:3 ratio display (or 3:4 for vertically oriented monitors like Pac-Man), it's difficult to find a consumer display that is 4:3 at this point. The good news is that that extra space on the sides isn't wasted. Many arcade cabinets used bezel artwork around the main display, and should you have the necessary artwork files, MAME will display that artwork. Turn the artwork view to Cropped for best results.

Some older LCD displays used a native resolution of 1280x1024 and were a 5:4 aspect ratio. There's not enough extra space to display artwork, and you'll end up with some very slight pillarboxing, but the results will be still be good and on-par with a 4:3 monitor.

Getting Started with HLSL

You will need to have followed the initial MAME setup instructions elsewhere in this manual before beginning. Official MAME distributions include HLSL by default, so you don't need to download any additional files.

Open your mame.ini in your text editor of choice (e.g. Notepad), and make sure the following options are set correctly:

video d3d

filter 0

The former is required because HLSL requires Direct3D support. The latter turns off extra filtering that interferes with HLSL output.

Lastly, one more edit will turn HLSL on:

hlsl_enable 1

Save the .INI file and you're ready to begin.

Several presets have been included in the INI folder with MAME, allowing for good quick starting points for Nintendo Game Boy, Nintendo Game Boy Advance, Raster, and Vector monitor settings.

Tweaking HLSL Settings inside MAME

For multiple, complicated to explain reasons, HLSL settings are no longer saved when you exit MAME. This means that while tweaking settings is a little more work on your part, the results will always come out as expected.

Start by loading MAME with the game of your choice (e.g. mame pacman)

The tilde key (~) brings up the on-screen display options. Use up and down to go through the various settings, while left and right will allow you to change that setting. Results will be shown in real time as you're changing these settings.

Once you've found settings you like, write the numbers down on a notepad and exit MAME.

Configuration Editing

As referenced in Order of Config Loading, MAME has a order in which it processes INI files. The HLSL settings can be edited in mame.ini, but to take full advantage of the power of MAME's config files, you'll want to copy the HLSL settings from mame.ini to one of the other config files and make changes there.

For instance, once you've found HLSL settings you think are appropriate for Neo Geo games, you can put those settings into neogeo.ini so that all Neo-Geo games will be able to take advantage of those settings without needing to add it to every game INI manually.

Configuration Settings

hlslpath

This is where your HLSL files are stored. By default, this will be the HLSL folder in your MAME installation.

hlsl_snap_width

hlsl_snap_height

Sets the resolution that Alt+F12 HLSL screenshots are output at.

shadow_mask_alpha (Shadow Mask Amount)

This defines how strong the effect of the shadowmask is. Acceptable range is from 0 to 1, where 0 will show no shadowmask effect, 1 will be a completely opaque shadowmask, and 0.5 will be 50% transparent.

shadow_mask_tile_mode (Shadow Mask Tile Mode)

This defines whether the shadowmask should be tiled based on the screen resolution of your monitor or based on the source resolution of the emulated system. Valid values are 0 for Screen mode and 1 for Source mode.

shadow_mask_texture

shadow_mask_x_count (Shadow Mask Pixel X Count)

shadow_mask_y_count (Shadow Mask Pixel Y Count)

shadow_mask_usize (Shadow Mask U Size)

shadow_mask_vsize (Shadow Mask V Size)

shadow_mask_x_count (Shadow Mask U Offset)

shadow_mask_y_count (Shadow Mask V Offset)

These settings need to be set in unison with one another. In particular, shadow_mask_texture sets rules for how you need to set the other options.

shadow_mask_texture sets the texture of the shadowmask effect. Three shadowmasks are included with MAME: aperture-grille.png, shadow-mask.png, and slot-mask.png

shadow_mask_usize and shadow_mask_vsize define the used size of the shadow_mask_texture in percentage, staring at the top-left corner. The means for a texture with the actual size of 24x24 pixel and an u/v size of 0.5,0.5 the top-left 12x12 pixel will be used. Keep in mind to define an u/v size that makes is possible to tile the texture without gaps or glitches. 0.5,0.5 is fine for any shadowmask texture that is included with MAME.

shadow_mask_x_count and shadow_mask_y_count define how many screen pixel should be used to display the u/v sized texture. e.g. if you use the example from above and define a x/y count of 12,12 every pixel of the texture will be displayed 1:1 on the screen, if you define a x/y count of 24,24 the texture will be displayed twice as large.

example settings for shadow_mask.png:

shadow_mask_texture shadow-mask.png

shadow_mask_x_count 12

shadow_mask_y_count 6 or 12

shadow_mask_usize 0.5

shadow_mask_vsize 0.5

example settings for slot-mask.png:

shadow_mask_texture slot-mask.png

shadow_mask_x_count 12

shadow_mask_y_count 8 or 16

shadow_mask_usize 0.5

shadow_mask_vsize 0.5

example settings for aperture-grille:

shadow_mask_texture aperture-grille.png

shadow_mask_x_count 12

shadow_mask_y_count 12 or any

shadow_mask_usize 0.5

shadow_mask_vsize 0.5

shadow_mask_uoffset and shadow_mask_voffset can be used to tweak the alignment of the final shadowmask in subpixel range. Range is from -1.00 to 1.00, where 0.5 moves the shadowmask by 50 percent of the u/v sized texture.

distortion (Quadric Distortion Amount)

This setting determines strength of the quadric distortion of the screen image.

cubic_distortion (Cubic Distortion Amount)

This setting determines strength of the cubic distortion of the screen image.

Both distortion factors can be negative to compensate each other. e.g. distortion 0.5 and cubic_distortion -0.5

distort_corner (Distorted Corner Amount)

This setting determines strength of distortion of the screen corners, which does not affect the distortion of screen image itself.

round_corner (Rounded Corner Amount)

The corners of the display can be rounded off through the use of this setting.

smooth_border (Smooth Border Amount)

Sets a smoothened/blurred border around the edges of the screen.

reflection (Reflection Amount)

If set above 0, this creates a white reflective blotch on the display. By default, this is put in the upper right corner of the display. By editing the POST.FX file's GetSpotAddend section, you can change the location. Range is from 0.00 to 1.00.

vignetting (Vignetting Amount)

When set above 0, will increasingly darken the outer edges of the display in a pseudo-3D effect. Range is from 0.00 to 1.00.

scanline_alpha (Scanline Amount)

This defines how strong the effect of the scanlines are. Acceptable range is from 0 to 1, where 0 will show no scanline effect, 1 will be a completely black line, and 0.5 will be 50% transparent. Note that arcade monitors did not have completely black scanlines.

scanline_size (Overall Scanline Scale)

The overall spacing of the scanlines is set with this option. Setting it at 1 represents consistent alternating spacing between display lines and scanlines.

scanline_height (Individual Scanline Scale)

This determines the overall size of each scanline. Setting lower than 1 makes them thinner, larger than 1 makes them thicker.

scanline_variation (Scanline Variation)

This affects the size of each scanline depending on its brightness. Brighter scanlines will be thicker than darker scanline. Acceptable range is from 0 to 2.0, with the default being 1.0. At 0.0 all scanlines will have the same size independent of their brightness.

scanline_bright_scale (Scanline Brightness Scale)

Specifies how bright the scanlines are. Larger than 1 will make them brighter, lower will make them dimmer. Setting to 0 will make scanlines disappear entirely.

scanline_bright_offset (Scanline Brightness Offset)

This will give scanlines a glow/overdrive effect, softening and smoothing the top and bottom of each scanline.

scanline_jitter (Scanline Jitter Amount)

Specifies the wobble or jitter of the scanlines, causing them to jitter on the monitor. Warning: Higher settings may hurt your eyes.

hum_bar_alpha (Hum Bar Amount)

Defines the strength of the hum bar effect.

defocus (Defocus)

This option will defocus the display, blurring individual pixels like an extremely badly maintained monitor. Specify as X,Y values (e.g. defocus 1,1)

converge_x (Linear Convergence X, RGB)

converge_y (Linear Convergence Y, RGB)

radial_converge_x (Radial Convergence X, RGB)

radial_converge_y (Radial Convergence Y, RGB)

Adjust the convergence of the red, green, and blue channels in a given direction. Many badly maintained monitors with bad convergence would bleed colored ghosting off-center of a sprite, and this simulates that.

red_ratio (Red Output from RGB)

grn_ratio (Green Output from RGB)

blu_ratio (Blue Output from RGB)

Defines a 3x3 matrix that is multiplied with the RGB signals to simulate color channel interference. For instance, a green channel of (0.100, 1.000, 0.250) is weakened 10% by the red channel and strengthened 25% through the blue channel.

offset (Signal Offset)

Strengthen or weakens the current color value of a given channel. For instance, a red signal of 0.5 with an offset of 0.2 will be raised to 0.7

scale (Signal Scale)

Applies scaling to the current color value of the channel. For instance, a red signal of 0.5 with a scale of 1.1 will result in a red signal of 0.55

power (Signal Exponent, RGB)

Exponentiate the current color value of the channel, also called gamma. For instance, a red signal of 0.5 with red power of 2 will result in a red signal of 0.25

This setting also can be used to adjust line thickness in vector games.

floor (Signal Floor, RGB)

Sets the absolute minimum color value of a channel. For instance, a red signal of 0.0 (total absence of red) with a red floor of 0.2 will result in a red signal of 0.2

Typically used in conjunction with artwork turned on to make the screen have a dim raster glow.

phosphor_life (Phosphor Persistence, RGB)

How long the color channel stays on the screen, also called phosphor ghosting. 0 gives absolutely no ghost effect, and 1 will leave a contrail behind that is only overwritten by a higher color value.

This also affects vector games quite a bit.

saturation (Color Saturation)

Color saturation can be adjusted here.

bloom_blend_mode (Bloom Blend Mode)

Determines the mode of the bloom effect. Valid values are 0 for Brighten mode and 1 for Darken mode, last is only useful for systems with STN LCD.

bloom_scale (Bloom Scale)

Determines the intensity of bloom effect. Arcade CRT displays had a tendency towards bloom, where bright colors could bleed out into neighboring pixels. This effect is extremely graphics card intensive, and can be turned completely off to save GPU power by setting it to 0

bloom_overdrive (Bloom Overdrive, RGB)

Sets a RGB color, separated by commas, that has reached the brightest possible color and will be overdriven to white. This is only useful on color raster, color LCD, or color vector games.

bloom_lvl0_weight (Bloom Level 0 Scale)

bloom_lvl1_weight (Bloom Level 1 Scale)

. . . .

bloom_lvl7_weight (Bloom Level 7 Scale)

bloom_lvl8_weight (Bloom Level 8 Scale)

These define the bloom effect. Range is from 0.00 to 1.00. If used carefully in conjunction with phosphor_life, glowing/ghosting for moving objects can be achieved.

hlsl_write

Enables writing of an uncompressed AVI video with the HLSL effects included with set to 1. This uses a massive amount of disk space very quickly, so a large HD with fast write speeds is highly recommended. Default is 0, which is off.

Suggested defaults for raster-based games:

bloom_lvl0_weight 1.00

bloom_lvl1_weight 0.64

bloom_lvl2_weight 0.32

bloom_lvl3_weight 0.16

bloom_lvl4_weight 0.08

bloom_lvl5_weight 0.06

bloom_lvl6_weight 0.04

bloom_lvl7_weight 0.02

bloom_lvl8_weight 0.01

|

Bloom level 0 weight

Bloom level 1 weight

Bloom level 2 weight

Bloom level 3 weight

Bloom level 4 weight

Bloom level 5 weight

Bloom level 6 weight

Bloom level 7 weight

Bloom level 8 weight

|

Full-size target.

1/4 smaller that level 0 target

1/4 smaller that level 1 target

1/4 smaller that level 2 target

1/4 smaller that level 3 target

1/4 smaller that level 4 target

1/4 smaller that level 5 target

1/4 smaller that level 6 target

1/4 smaller that level 7 target

Vector Games

HLSL effects can also be used with vector games. Due to a wide variance of vector settings to optimize for each individual game, it is heavily suggested you add these to per-game INI files (e.g. tempest.ini)

Shadowmasks were only present on color vector games, and should not be used on monochrome vector games. Additionally, vector games did not use scanlines, so that should also be turned off.

Open your INI file in your text editor of choice (e.g. Notepad), and make sure the following options are set correctly:

video d3d

filter 0

hlsl_enable 1

In the Core Vector Options section:

beam_width_min 1.0 (Beam Width Minimum)

beam_width_max 1.0 (Beam Width Maximum)

beam_intensity_weight 0.0 (Beam Intensity Weight)

flicker 0.0 (Vector Flicker)

In the Vector Post-Processing Options section:

vector_beam_smooth 0.0 (Vector Beam Smooth Amount)

vector_length_scale 0.5 (Vector Attenuation Maximum)

vector_length_ratio 0.5 (Vector Attenuation Length Minimum)

Suggested settings for vector games:

bloom_scale should typically be set higher for vector games than raster games. Try between 0.4 and 1.0 for best effect.

bloom_overdrive should only be used with color vector games.

bloom_lvl_weights should be set as follows:

bloom_lvl0_weight 1.00

bloom_lvl1_weight 0.48

bloom_lvl2_weight 0.32

bloom_lvl3_weight 0.24

bloom_lvl4_weight 0.16

bloom_lvl5_weight 0.24

bloom_lvl6_weight 0.32

bloom_lvl7_weight 0.48

bloom_lvl8_weight 0.64

|

Bloom level 0 weight

Bloom level 1 weight

Bloom level 2 weight

Bloom level 3 weight

Bloom level 4 weight

Bloom level 5 weight

Bloom level 6 weight

Bloom level 7 weight

Bloom level 8 weight

|

Full-size target.

1/4 smaller that level 0 target

1/4 smaller that level 1 target

1/4 smaller that level 2 target

1/4 smaller that level 3 target

1/4 smaller that level 4 target

1/4 smaller that level 5 target

1/4 smaller that level 6 target

1/4 smaller that level 7 target

Linux Lightguns

Many lightguns (especially the Ultimarc AimTrak) may work better in MAME under Linux when using a slightly more complicated configuration. The instructions here are for getting an AimTrak working on Ubuntu using udev and Xorg, but other Linux distributions and lightguns may work with some changes to the steps.

Configure udev rules

For the AimTrak, each lightgun exposes several USB devices once connected: 2 mouse emulation devices, and 1 joystick emulation device. We need to instruct libinput via udev to ignore all but the correct emulated mouse device. This prevents each lightgun from producing multiple mouse devices, which would result in non-deterministic selection between the "good" and "bad" emulated mouse devices by Xorg.

Create a new file named /etc/udev/rules.d/65-aimtrak.rules and place the following contents into it:

# Set mode (0666) & disable libinput handling to avoid X11 picking up the wrong

# interfaces/devices.

SUBSYSTEMS=="usb", ATTRS{idVendor}=="d209", ATTRS{idProduct}=="160*",

MODE="0666", ENV{ID_INPUT}="", ENV{LIBINPUT_IGNORE_DEVICE}="1"

# For ID_USB_INTERFACE_NUM==2, re-enable libinput handling.

SUBSYSTEMS=="usb", ATTRS{idVendor}=="d209", ATTRS{idProduct}=="160*",

ENV{ID_USB_INTERFACE_NUM}=="02", ENV{ID_INPUT}="1",

ENV{LIBINPUT_IGNORE_DEVICE}="0"

This configuration will be correct for the AimTrak lightguns, however each brand of lightgun will require their own settings.

Configure Xorg inputs

Next, we'll configure Xorg to treat the lightguns as a "Floating" device. This is important for multiple lightguns to work correctly and ensures each gun's emulated mouse pointer is NOT merged with the main system mouse pointer.

In /etc/X11/xorg.conf.d/60-aimtrak.conf we will need:

Section "InputClass"

Identifier "AimTrak Guns"

MatchDevicePath "/dev/input/event*"

MatchUSBID "d209:160*"

Driver "libinput"

Option "Floating" "yes"

Option "AutoServerLayout" "no"

EndSection

Configure MAME

Next, we'll need to configure MAME via mame.ini to use the new lightgun device(s).

lightgun 1

lightgun_device lightgun

lightgunprovider x11

These first three lines tell MAME to enable lightgun support, to tell MAME that we're using a lightgun instead of a mouse, and to use the x11 provider.

lightgun_index1 "Ultimarc ATRAK Device #1"

lightgun_index2 "Ultimarc ATRAK Device #2"

lightgun_index3 "Ultimarc ATRAK Device #3"

lightgun_index4 "Ultimarc ATRAK Device #4"

These next lines then tell MAME to keep lightguns consistent across sessions.

offscreen_reload 1

Lastly, as most lightgun games require offscreen reloading and we're using a device that actually can point away from the screen, we enable that functionality.

Multiple Configuration Files

MAME has a very powerful configuration file system that can allow you to tweak settings on a per-game, per-system, or even per-monitor type basis, but requires careful thought about how you arrange your configs.

Order of Config Loading

The command line is parsed first, and any settings passed that way will take precedence over anything in an INI file.

mame.ini (or other platform INI; e.g. mess.ini) is parsed twice. The first pass may change various path settings, so the second pass is done to see if there is a valid configuration file at that new location (and if so, change settings using that file).

debug.ini if the debugger is enabled. This is an advanced config file, most people won't need to use it or be concerned by it.

Screen orientation INI file (either horizont.ini or vertical.ini). For example Pac-Man has a vertical screen, so it loads vertical.ini, while Street Fighter Alpha uses a horizontal screen, so it loads horizont.ini.

Systems with no monitors, multiple monitors with different orientations, or monitors connected to slot devices will usually load horizont.ini.

Monitor type INI file (vector.ini for vector monitors, raster.ini for CRT raster monitors, or lcd.ini for LCD/EL/plasma matrix monitors). Pac-Man and Street Fighter Alpha use raster CRTs, so raster.ini is loaded here, while Tempest uses a vector monitor, so vector.ini is loaded here.

For systems that have multiple monitor types, such as House Mannequin with its CRT raster monitor and dual LCD matrix monitors, the INI file relevant to the first monitor is used (raster.ini in this case). Systems without monitors or with other kinds of monitors will not load an INI file for this step.

Driver source file INI file. MAME will attempt to load source/<sourcefile>.ini where <sourcefile> is the base name of the source code file where the system driver is defined. A system's source file can be found using mame -listsource <pattern> at the command line.

For instance, Banpresto's Sailor Moon, Atlus's Dodonpachi, and Nihon System's Dangun Feveron all run on similar hardware and are defined in the cave.cpp source file, so they will all load source/cave.ini at this step.

BIOS set INI file (if applicable). For example The Last Soldier uses the Neo-Geo MVS BIOS, so it will load neogeo.ini. Systems that don't use a BIOS set won't load an INI file for this step.

Parent system INI file. For example The Last Soldier is a clone of The Last Blade / Bakumatsu Roman - Gekka no Kenshi, so it will load lastblad.ini. Parent systems will not load an INI file for this step.

System INI file. Using the previous example, The Last Soldier will load lastsold.ini.

Examples of Config Loading Order

Brix, which is a clone of Zzyzzyxx. (mame brix)

Command line

mame.ini (global)

(debugger not enabled, no extra INI file loaded)

vertical.ini (screen orientation)

raster.ini (monitor type)

source/jack.ini (driver source file)

(no BIOS set)

zzyzzyxx.ini (parent system)

brix.ini (system)

Super Street Fighter 2 Turbo (mame ssf2t)

Command line

mame.ini (global)

(debugger not enabled, no extra INI file loaded)

horizont.ini (screen orientation)

raster.ini (monitor type)

source/cps2.ini (driver source file)

(no BIOS set)

(no parent system)

ssf2t.ini (system)

Final Arch (mame finlarch)

Command line

mame.ini (global)

(debugger not enabled, no extra INI file loaded)

horizont.ini (screen orientation)

raster.ini (monitor type)

source/stv.ini (driver source file)

stvbios.ini (BIOS set)

smleague.ini (parent system)

finlarch.ini (system)

Remember command line parameters take precedence over all else!

Tricks to Make Life Easier

Some users may have a wall-mounted or otherwise rotatable monitor, and may wish to actually play vertical games with the rotated display. The easiest way to accomplish this is to put your rotation modifiers into vertical.ini, where they will only affect vertical games.